Guide to the William Seward Burroughs Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William Seward Burroughs Papers,
1957-1976.
Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.
2 linear ft (5 document boxes and 1 oversize item).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
MS#0174
4078569
Author, artist, spoken word performer, and founding member of the Beat Generation. The William S. Burroughs Papers contain manuscripts and galley proofs of some of Burroughs's novels, as well as biographical material on Burroughs.
Biographical Note
William S. Burroughs was born in 1914 in St. Louis, Missouri. He attended private schools in St. Louis before a brief stint at the Los Alamos Ranch School in New Mexico. He received a bachelor's degree from Harvard in 1936.
After graduating from Harvard, Burroughs spent a few years traveling through Europe, followed by a short stint in the US Army. After his discharge from the Army Burroughs moved to Chicago where he worked a string of odd jobs and spent time with his friend David Kammerer and Kammerer's obsession, University of Chicago student Lucien Carr. When Carr transferred from UC to Columbia University, both of the older men used this as an impetus to move to New York City as well.
It was through Carr that Burroughs met Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac. The three, along with Carr, Kerouac's girlfriend Edie Parker and her roommate Joan Vollmer, forged close friendships centered around a shared love of literature, drugs, and a bohemian lifestyle. It was during this time that Burroughs was first introduced to narcotics through the well known Times Square hustler, and writer, Herbert Huncke and quickly became addicted to opiates. Jean Vollmer, Burroughs's lover, and later common-law wife, also suffered from an addiction that eventually resulted in her hospitalization for acute amphetamine psychosis. The two had a son, William S. Burroughs Jr., before Burroughs accidentally, but fatally, shot Vollmer in Mexico City.
Burroughs began working on the manuscript that would eventually become Junky in Mexico City before Vollmer's death. Though he had briefly worked on the short story "And the Hippos Were Boiled in Their Tanks" with Jack Kerouac, he did not have literary aspirations. Even while working on Junkie he assumed that the autobiographical novel would be an anomaly, not the beginning of a literary career.
After his trial over Vollmer's death, Burroughs thought it prudent to leave Mexico. He spent more time traveling in South America researching the hallucinatory drug yage and corresponding with Allen Ginsberg, who was by this point acting as his literary agent, about his search for the drug and its effects. These letters formed the basis of Burroughs and Ginsberg's book The Yage Letters. After the yage quest, Burroughs returned, briefly, to New York where he initiated an intense but mostly one-sided romantic and sexual relationship with Ginsberg before leaving the United States for a brief stay in Rome and then Tangier.
While in Tangier Burroughs completed the text that would become The Naked Lunch. Interzone, as he called the working manuscript, was, in opposition to his earlier works Junkie and Queer, a non-linear collection of loosely connected episodes. Allen Ginsberg, who, along with Peter Orlovsky and Jack Kerouac, had traveled to Tangier to help collect and type a clean copy of the manuscript, presented The Naked Lunch to Maurice Girodias of the Olympia Press. Though Girodias was not initially interested in the work, he did decide to print it after all in 1959. An American edition, based on a 1958 manuscript of the novel (currently part of the Allen Ginsberg Papers held by the RBML) was published by Grove Press in 1962.
Burroughs then moved to Paris where he continued writing and producing the episodic sketches that, combined with material from The Naked Lunch manuscripts, comprise The Soft Machine, The Ticket that Exploded, and Nova Express. While in Paris living in a guesthouse christened the Beat Hotel with Ginsberg, Orlovsky, Gergory Corso, and Harold Chapman, Burroughs first came into contact with Brion Gysin. Gysin, a painter, had a profound impact on Burroughs and Gysin's "cut-up technique" where strips of two different texts were aligned to create a new, composite text became a prominent feature of Burroughs's future writing.
In 1974 Burroughs returned to the United States. He accepted a teaching post at City College of New York that Allen Ginsberg had recommended him for and settled into an apartment nicknamed The Bunker on Manhattan's Lower East Side. During this time Burroughs became acquainted with James Grauerholz, a young beat devotee who became Burroughs's devoted manager, secretary, and companion.
Burroughs moved to Lawrence Kansas in 1981 and remained there until his death in 1997. During the later part of his life he wrote less and less, focusing on visual art and spoken word performances. He also appears in the Gus Van Sant movie Naked Cowboy.
Scope and Content
The William S. Burroughs Papers contain manuscripts and galley proofs of some of Burroughs's novels, as well as experimental prose, including early examples of Burroughs's cut-up technique, and a small amount of correspondence. The collection also contains a series of biographical material on Burroughs collected by Victor Bockris.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1953-1973
Series II: Writings, 1958-1969
Series III: Photographs and Realia
Series IV: Victor Bockris Material Relating to Burroughs, 1965-1975
Subjects
Bockris, Victor, 1949-; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; American literature.; Beat generation.; Galley proofs.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1959 M-59
Alternate Formats
William Burroughs letters are on microfilm.
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Allen Ginsberg Papers, 1944-1991 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
The Ginsberg Papers contain some correspondence, some additional experimental prose, and fractionary drafts of The Exterminator, Queer, and "The Hot Rod" as well as a full manuscript of The Naked Lunch (here referred to by the working title "Interzone.")
Jack Kerouac Correspondence, 1945-1965 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barry Miles Papers, 1958-1990 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ann Charters Photographs, 1966-1982 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Naked Lunch: The First Fifty Years online exhibition, Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Selected Related Material-- Other Repositories
William S. Burroughs Papers New York Public Library, Berg Collection
William S. Burroughs Papers, WSB 97 Ohio State University, Rare Books and Manuscripts
William S. Burroughs Collection Hayden Library Special Collections, Arizona State University
- Series I: Correspondence, 1953-1973
  The Correspondence series contains a few select pieces of correspondence between Burroughs and his friends and collaborators. In this series are letters exchanged between Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg regarding their collaborative, epistolary book The Yage Letters. This series, though small, includes both letters later reprinted as part of the publication and correspondence related to the editing and process.
  - Burroughs to Bill Berkson, June 4, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burroughs to Allen Ginsberg
    - January 25, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      (published as part of The Yage Letters)
    - January 6, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (regarding The Yage Letters)
    - January 9, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - March 9, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Allen Ginsberg to Burroughs, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Philip Whalen to Burroughs, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Writings, 1958-1969
  The Writings series is the largest series in the collection and contains working drafts of 1961's Grove Press Edition of The Soft Machine, as well as annotated drafts and galley proofs of Burroughs's substantial 1965 revision of the novel published by Grove Press. There are also drafts and galleys of Nova Express; a corrected, signed galley proof of The Naked Lunch; and full typescript drafts of The Yage Letters and Junkie. This series also contains a collection of prose experiments conducted by Burroughs utilizing the cut-up technique that he utilized in much of his longer fiction, as well as experiments in using a grid form to intersplice different texts together.
  - "A Brief Statement on The Naked Lunch The Soft Machine and The Nova Express," circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    (carbon copy in WSB's hand)
  - Dealer Catalogs and Book Reviews (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Epic Prose Poem," circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Experimental Prose, circa 1958-1965, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-16)
  - "Johnny 23" (with Editor's Corrections) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Junkie-- Manuscript (Box 5)
  - The Naked Lunch
    - Signed Galley Proofs (Box 1, Folder 18)
      (original proof, 1964 Burroughs's signature, 1969)
    - Recording of Burroughs reading Naked Lunch, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Please follow these links for digitized clips of the sections The Rube, Meeting of International Conference..., and The Exterminator Does a Good Job
  - Nova Express (Box 2)
    - Early Drafts, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Galley Proofs, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Soft Machine
    - Typescript with autograph corrections, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      (for 1961 Olympia Press Edition)
    - Typescript with autograph corrections, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (formed the basis for the 1963 Grove Press edition)
    - Galley Proofs- Grove Press Edition, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Related Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Strange Bed," circa 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Yage Letters- Draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Photographs and Realia
  The photographs in the collection are mostly snapshots of Burroughs and Herbert Huncke. Also included in this series is the Dreamachine, a device designed by Burroughs and Brion Gysin and constructed by Ian Sommerville, designed to help stimulate brain activity and bring about a hallucinatory state.
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dreamachine (Box 14)
- Series IV: Victor Bockris Files, 1965-1975
  Victor Bockris, a friend and collaborator of Burroughs, Victor Bockris write several articles about Burroughs and edited both Burroughs's collection of essays, The Adding Machine and the interview-based book With William Burroughs: A Report from the Bunker. This series of material includes numerous drafts of and notes for With William Burroughs, as well as some of Burroughs's published writings collected by Bockris- including a small run of Crawdaddy Magazines featuring articles or columns by Burroughs and a copy of The Paris Review that includes both an interview with Burroughs and his essay "St. Louis Return."
  - Correspondence and Ephemera (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - With William Burroughs
    - Draft-- Preface with Barry Miles Comments 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Drafts and Notes, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 5)
    - Drafts and Notes, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Notes on Burroughs, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Collected Burroughs Writings
    - Black Mask, August, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      (contains Burroughs's "Coldspring News")
    - The Paris Review, Fall, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      (contains Burroughs's "St. Louis Return" and an interview with Burroughs)
    - Crawdaddy, June-December, 1975, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 6 to 7)
    - New York Arts Journal, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
      (includes Bockris interview with Burroughs)
    - The Drummer, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)